Albert Van Dusen Papers
© 2010 University of Connecticut
- Inventory, undated
  - Dates include: 1723/24 - 1785, 1 July 1730 - 4 September 1730 - 24 December 1759 (Box 94)
    Trumbull sermon notes, commonplace book, correspondence, journal notes, general notes.
  - (Box 95)
    Lebanon church records, proprietors record book, mohegan case documents, records. misc. photocopies of letters. photocopied excerpts from "the currency of the American colonies". records from ecclesiastical society and lebanon congregational church. photocopies of publications on Lebanon, CT.
  - 26 May 1758 - 3 October 1763 (Box 96)
    Correspondence marked "unedited"
  - Dates include: 1752, 1752 - 1769. 1, 16 January, 18 Febuary, 10, 20, 24 and March 1751/52. 13 April 1752 - 30 August 1755. (Box 97)
    "unedited correspondence"
  - Dates include 26 July 1749 - 25 September 1756 (Box 98)
    Correspondence, bills, General Assembly matters. Photocopies and photostats. Spanish ship case documents. Unedited documents. Sasquehammack Case and papers. Housing plans.
  - 1751 - 1756 (Box 99)
    Photocopied and typed transcripts of letters and documents. Original copy/manuscript of book entitled "Connecticut". Copy of Van Dusen's "Connecticut".
  - (Box 100)
    Trumbull correspondence and photocopies of Trumbull history and documents.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1960s-1994, undated (Box 101)
    Correspondence with various musuems, historical societies, colleges, committees and associations. Book reviews as well as annoucement for Van Dusen's retiring from Uconn (1983)
  - Personal and professional papers, 1950's-1970's (Box 102)
    Student work as well as graded student work. Correspondence with students. Class papers; old exam sheets, syllabus for each class, field trips, reading assingments, study abroad pamphlets. Also material on grant proposals.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1970's-1980's (Box 103)
    classes taught by Van Dusen including syllabi, reading lists, field trips possibly graded student work. Newspaper clippings, grant information and correspondence with museums and historical societies. Various information on the Trumbull papers including publication information on the frist volume of the Trumbull papers. Correspondence with the AASLH including nominations and awards.
  - Professional papers, undated (Box 104)
    This box contains Jonathan Trumbull documents. Some are undated, others are labeled that Van Dusen did not use them. Some are labeled 1790-1829. Also the Commonplace book of Jonathan Trumbull
  - (Box 105)
    Personal items and papers of Van Dusen including catalogs, letters, invitations, postcards, Connecticut papers. Photoduplication policies/procedures for various U.S. libraries. Van Dusen correspondence, real estate info, office memos, and various historical articles. Staff concerns regarding Trumbull Papers. Report on ledgers E and F of Trumbull (Box 74). Personal service agreements and other papers regarding the Trumbull Papers Project. Photostats and photocopies of historical documents.
  - Dates include: 1759 - 1760, 1759 - 1762, 29 June 1761 - 12 September 1761 (Box 106)
    photocopies and photostats of Trumbull diary (1759 - 1760) (carbon copy included) and account book (1759 - 1762). Trumbull correspondence ( 29 June 1761 - 12 September 1761). Publications about Mystic and maritime history. One book on the Third Reich. Notecards on Lebanon Church Records vol. II. Biographical notecards.
  - (Box 107)
    Section of file collections beginning with Nathaniel Greene and ending on the letter R. Information on libraries and people, projects, archives.
  - 1940 - 1945 (Box 108)
    Letters, personal notebooks, yearbooks, examinations, and personal items of Albert Van Dusen's wife. Much of the material in this box
  - 1724 - 1749 (Box 109)
    Final copy of xeroxes of Trumbull sermon notes, correspondence (Van Dusen handwritten notes included)
  - (Box 110)
    Photocopies of handwritten notes on Trumbull and correspondence between Trumbull and associates.
  - Roughly 1970 - 1977 (Box 111)
    UConn files 1970 - 1977 concerning graduate school, intradepartmental notices, newsletters, exc.
  - 1757 - 1761, 1753 - 1772 (Box 112)
    Xeroxes of historical documents, correspondence, and pages from ledger. Ledger G.
  - 1754 - 9 May 1764 (Box 113)
    Correspondence, Albany Plan of Union.
  - 20 August 1750 - 25 June 1752 (Box 114)
    Trumbull correspondence
  - 5 May 1760 - 7 September 1770 (Box 115)
    Trumbull's reflections on becoming a minister, notes and support, draft for articles of consideration, correspondence between listed dates, list of armies.
  - Dates include: April/May 1764, June/July - December 1752, July/September 1756. October/November 1756, Febuary 1757, July/September 1755, 1754, October/December 1763, January - March 1764, 1775 - 1776, 1767 - 1773, 1778 - 1791, 1804 - 1809, 1744 - 1755, 1758, 1760 - 1763, 1744 - 1763 (Box 116)
    Trumbull correspondence with notes, record book, inventory list, Joseph Trumbull Papers, Norwich Town Records, Connecticut Historical Society (Hadly), French and Indian War Papers, David Trumbull Papers.
  - Dates include 1739 - 1749, 1729 - 1749 (Box 117)
    Collection of postcards from Van Dusen, original typescripts (1739 - 1749), photostat copies of historical documents, Van Dusen personal letters, 1729 - 1749 manuscript typed by Van Dusen for Trumbull Papers, biographical photocopies.
  - (Box 118)
    Photostats of General Assmebly papers,
  - Dates listed below (Box 119)
    Documents from Yale (1767 - 1822) including 1772 Yale commencement. Lebanon map 1769 - 1779. Pension files. National Archives files. Joseph Trumbull's probate files. Correspondence (September 1776 - April 1780)
  - (Box 120)
    Spanish ship case (7 October 1754 - March 1756). Nova Scotia papers (8 December 1760 - 19 June 1769). Correspondence (1759 - 1766).
  - (Box 121)
    Documents on Trumbull house and family. Biographical material on historical figures and deeds. Harvard faculty records. Land holdings, records, deeds and misc. items. Three black notebooks containing manuscripts of Trumbull papers and correspondence.
  - (Box 122)
    General Gage to Governor Trumbull. Misc. notes. History of Trumbull papers. Assorted publications from UConn. *Box needs review for extraneous and unncessary material*
  - (Box 123)
    Informational packets on microfilm process including catalogs and manuals. Microfilm project for Trumbull project including grant applications and information. Abstracts and proposals for Trumbull project. Time cards reporting hours worked at state library by assistants of Van Dusen (potential for removal).
  - (Box 124)
    Assorted photocopies of historical papers: Narragansett Historical Register, papers on emigration and settlement of Nova Scotia, Historical Register, Diary of Jabez Fitch. Photostats, maps, and notecards.
  - (Box 125)
    Photocopies of articles on colonial figures- last names beginning with F - L.
  - (Box 126)
    Photocopies of articles on colonial figures- L-S
  - Professional papers, 1970's, undated (Box 127)
    Various correspondence with organizations. Information on Jonathan Trumbull paper including annual and quarterly reports on the progress of the project. Book reviews by Van Dusen
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 128)
    Box reads: Index puritans Against the Wilderness A-Z. All hand written, possibly for a book or article.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1960's, undated (Box 129)
    Information on various towns in connecitcut and various correspondence. A large part of this box contians Van Dusen's book Commonplace all typed all chapters in own individual folders. Also includes footnotes. Van Dusen's academic and non academic activities (1964-67)
  - Personal and professional papers, 1982-1985, Undated (Box 130)
    Various correspondence including correspondence about Jonathan Trumbull papers. Information about Van Dusen being the Connecticut state historian. More personal information such as travel plans and plans for retirement.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1980's,undated (Box 131)
    Various correspondence including correspondence about Jonathan Trumbull papers. A large amount of correspondence with the Antiquarian and Landmarks society.
  - (Box 132)
    Manuscript of Trumbull notes on becoming a minister (original typescript 1724 - January 1738/39). Revised grant application. AVD files. Photostats of documents and notes.
  - (Box 133)
    Booklets/historical magazines, interviews, photostats. *Box needs review for extraneous and unncessary material*
  - Personal and professional papers, 1960's-1990's, undated (Box 134)
    Various correspondence including to with the AASLH about awards. Correspondence regarding Jonathan Trumbull papers. Personal correspondence with friends as well as a large section about Van and Wilda's travels (including travel arrangements, expenses,menus and maps. Correspondence with the connecticut Judicial department
  - Personal papers, 1970's-1980's, undated (Box 135)
    Personal letters to Wilda and Van from friends. Also invitations and newspaper clippings
  - (Box 136)
    Folders relevant to Van Dusen's career as a historian. Folders are in alphabetical order and contain everything from lecture guides, CHS and other historical society newsletters, graduate student publications, history of Trumbull papers
  - (Box 137)
    Notecards on lectures given by Van Dusen, information on American Colonial History, newspaper clippings, photographic transparencies, library/archives request documents, research notecards. *Box needs review for extraneous and unncessary material*
  - (Box 138)
    Folders containing Van Dusen correspondence (largely between 1970-72), lecture/speech matierals, pictures,
  - Personal and Professional papers, 1980's-1990's, undated (Box 139)
    Various correspondence including with the AASLH about nominies. There is also announcemnt of an award for distiction for Van presented by the AASLH. Also correspondence reguarding the Trumbull papers. Van's travel logs and planners from 1962-1973 are also included. Also some of Van's medical records.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1970's, undated (Box 140)
    Various historical reports done by Van Dusen, miscellaneous correspondence and some photocopied material on Jonathan Trumbull. Also a copy of Van's book Puritains against the Wilderness: CT history to 1763 copyright 1975. Correspondence with library commission and various awards given to Van Dusen
  - (Box 141)
    Correspondence, cards (at this time Van Dusen is already physically not well), information on Reep family, class record books containing names and grades, newspaper clippings on Van Dusen speeches, pictures. *Box needs review for extraneous and unncessary material*
  - (Box 142)
    Estate information (items in house were appraised), meeting minutes and notices, correspondence, newsletters from comittees/societies, publications, and evaluations. Material from Van Dusen's teaching days.
  - Personal and professional papers, 1980's, undated (Box 143)
    Personal correspondence (1983-860. Paper reviews, talks given by Van Dusen. Various correspondence including correspondence with AASLH and regarding Jonathan Trumbull papers. Big folder on caner. Cancer articles and pamphlets. Also Wilda's medical record of having brest cancer
  - Note cards, undated (Box 144)
    This box contains various stacks of note cards from various boxes of Van Dusen's personal and professional boxes. Some contain bibliographical information on Jonathan Trumbull (two sets of these, one hand written the other typed.)Also cards with notes and quotes on them dealing with colonial tradein late 17th and early 18th centuries. Next set contains information on Norwich CT (mostly people and places). Miscellaneous photograph as well as a whole stack of note cards with the sources crossed off.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 145)
    Several sections of note cards are in this box. Sections include; research slips, various libraries, random references, biog. search file, editing(ideas), bibliography of Trbl books, inter-library loan, journals of cont. congress. Many if not all sources having to do with Jonathan Trumbull.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 146)
    Box says, Library-state of CT 30 oak street. Hartford. A-H. Although not identified, this is a list of people only living in late 1600's and 1700's-early 1800's. Most if not all of these people are from CT.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 147)
    Front of the box reads Accession No. file 2300-4699. Cards are all typed and numbered 2300-4699 and are bibliographical information on wether a particular source was to, from or about Jonathan Trumbull
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 148)
    This is a continuation of box 146. This box is I-Z and contains the same information as box 146.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 149)
    Front of the box reads Maritime CT. Box contains index A-W. Based on title of the box and content, this box appears to be about CT maritime activities. Ships trading, whaling and also cards on Europe(possibly trading). Not marked what project they are for but in the front there are a few pictures of what looks like Wilda and Van skiing.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 150)
    Box says chron file 1764-75. Note cards are grouped by year so the card numbers are all out of order. All of them are about Jonathan Trumbull, either to, from or about him.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 151)
    (This is a big box with three rows of note cards and each row will need individual box when new boxes arrive but the next three boxes are all from the same original box labeled File #2 A.E. Van Dusen). First row is from Neal-Sarah (all typed). All about Jonathan Trumbull broken down into towns, subjects and people about documents to, from and about Jonathan Trumbull.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 152)
    This box is the continuation of box 151. It goes from Sarah-Ga-JT, Bus. Act. 1754.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 153)
    This is a continuation from box 152. It goes from JT, Bus. Act, 1775-Younghusband.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 154)
    Box is labeled 1771-. Note cards are alphabetical from A-I. They are of people who grew up in Connecticut, where they ended up and what occupation if known (mostly if not all males).
  - Note cards, undated (Box 155)
    Card in front of the box describes the content. It is Connecticut bibliography. A selected list of material in the Connectiuct state library dealing with the state. Items are arranged alphabetically by author with general subjects in red at the top of the card.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 156)
    Box reads Town (N.L)-WWII. There is a card in the front of the box listing all the sections (there are nearly 100) all having to do with CT. There is also a large section on CT towns.
  - Note Cards, Undated (Box 157)
    Box contains bibliographical information (for an unidentified project) mostly of men and a few women from CT. Alphabetically D-H.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 158)
    Box contains information on location and what documents different places have on Jonathan Trumbull. Plances include Penn archives, Mass. Historical society, CHS card catalogue, Yale and Rhode Island records.
  - (Box 159)
    Cardboard tubes filled with rolled up certificates, genealogical trees of historical figures, awards, retirement notice. Box containing casette tapes and film about history of CT from prehistoric times onwards. Manila envelope containing transcript of interviews with James Barnett along with tapes. Pictures of Van Duse. *Marked for preservation of some materials within*
  - (Box 160)
    History department newsletters, newspaper articles on Van Dusen, essay by Wilda Reep, misc. correspondence, retirement certificate
  - Note Cards, Undated (Box 161)
    All typed (A-I) regarding Jonathan Trumbull documents (bibliographical information) about letters to, from and about Jonathan Trumbull as well as places concerning J.Trumbull(General Assembly).
  - Note Cards, Undated (Box 162)
    All typed (U-Z). All regarding J. Trumbull. Bibliographical notes all about letters to, from and about J.Trumbull. Most of the box is named old accession numbers (half the box contains different set of note cards) where it also has to do with J.Trumbull but it is in numerical order rather than Alphabetical by last name.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 163)
    All typed. First half of the box is in numerical order, second half is in chronological order (1775-60) of when written (not duplicates in same box). All are note cards have to do with letters to, from and about Jonathan Trumbull.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 164)
    All about J. Trumbull. Bibliographical information (1776-1778).
  - Note cards, undated (Box 165)
    Box reads, Ledger index(H-S). Bibliographical information of people listed Alphabetically by last name. Most people from CT.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 166)
    Same information as box 165, just second half of index (T-Y).
  - Note cards, undated (Box 167)
    First in index order to boxes 165 and 166 but this contains index (A-G). Same information and a note card in the front of box listing the few exceptions to people in this series.
  - Note cards, undated (Box 168)
    Box reads Ledger and ACCTS Huntington-Porter, Noah. Listed in alphabetical order by last name. Contains bibliographical information of people, mostly from CT.
  - Note cards, Undated (Box 169)
    Box reads, Ledgers, ACCT books "B-Cutting, Thos." This is a continuation of previous box.
  - (Box 170)
    Graduate student information (their doctoral progress), information/notes on lectures, courses, colleagues, publicity,
  - (Box 171)
    Newspaper clippings, course notes/guides, correspondence (heavy emphasis on correspondence related to royalites and finances). *Box needs review for extraneous and unnecessary material*
  - (Box 172)
    Newsletters/items from various historical societies that Van Dusen was a part of, some financial information is present *marked for removal under the titled "public serviceS"*, manila envelopes containing information on Van Dusen's foster child in Italy (numerous folders entitled Domenico)
  - (Box 173)
    Typescript of "Puritans against the Wilderness" and a page proof. Many folders with information and writings on the Pequots. Chapters divided into folders from "Puritans against the Wilderness" on Pequot Press.
  - (Box 174)
    Notecards containing notes on historical figures, events, and places (most likely for lectures and speeches). Budgetary papers. Correspondence, abstract, drafts, and chapers for dissertation (?). Folder marked "Courant" was removed for preservation.
  - (Box 175)
    Van Dusen correspondence *marked for review*. Two small boxes filled with notecards: one contains information on events and figures between the years 1800 and 1801 gathed from various Connecticut news publications mainly Connecticut Courant and Am. Mercury. The other contains notes on elections 1924, 1926, 1928 and politics of that time. Personal papers of Van Dusen and records of Trumbull correspondence with small notes on content.
  - (Box 176)
    Misc. papers (photocopies, letters) *marked for review* in no immediate order or arrangement. Newsletters. Wilda's correspondence in box arranged alphabetically. Diary.
  - (Box 177)
    Framed awards given to Van Dusen over the span of his career.
  - (Box 178)
    *Marked for review*- Date planners, financial information, and other personal items. In addition to these items there is the original picture of a Connecticut house used by Van Dusen for his book "Connecticut" sent to him by Random House Inc.
  - (Box 179)
    Folders containing information on research at Sterlin Memorial Library and the Library of Congress organized into respective folders. Many notecards presumably on documents read at the libraries (in no particular arrangement).
  - (Box 180)
    *Marked for review* Personal items of Wilda (reunion information, cards, exc), various committee newsletters, government papers, army papers. Two black ledgers containing copy of "Connecticut" in final stage with pictures and everthing else. Manuscripts of "Connecticut" and "John Trumbull's Commonplace book". Correspondence (job offers and other information).
  - (Box 181)
    Photostats of Trumbull documents, Maritime documents, and photocopies/photostats of correspondence and other historical documents. *Marked for review: items of research interest should be organized better and placed earlier in the collection with other relevant documents*. Some items have been removed from original box for preservation (pictures). Personal papers.
  - (Box 182)
    Misc. papers (kept in folders). Correspondence ranging from 1956 - 1980+. Local societies/committees newsletters and documents. Lecture notes, graduate school letters, and other personal papers.
  - (Box 183)
    Pictures (contained in Kodax boxes) used in Van Dusen's "Connecticut". Rolled up photostats of Trumbull letters. Paintings (?). Trumbull correspondence. *Marked for preservation*
  - (Box 184)
    Illustration negatives (used in "Connecticut". Misc. Van Dusen correspondnece (not arranged). Condolence cards and letters sent to Wilda after Van Dusen's death.